[Music]
so earlier in section 2 where we talked
about nodes module system you learned
about this HTTP module we use this to
create a web server that listens on port
3000 and responds to requests for these
endpoints so the route or such API slash
courses now while this approach is
perfectly fine it's not ideal for
building a complex application because
in a large complex application we might
have various endpoints and we don't want
to hard-code all these if statements in
this function so in this section we're
going to look at Express which is a fast
and lightweight framework for building
web applications so next we're gonna
look at restful services
let's start the section by a brief
introduction to restful services also
called restful api s-- if you already
know what rest is all about feel free to
skip this video so earlier at the
beginning of the course I introduced you
to the client-server architecture so
most if not all applications we use
these days
follow this architecture the app itself
is the client or the front-end part
under the hood it needs to talk to a
server or the back-end to get or save
the data this communication happens
using the HTTP protocol the same
protocol that powers our web so on the
server we expose a bunch of services
that are accessible via the HTTP
protocol the client can then directly
call the services by sending HTTP
requests now this is where rest comes
into the picture
rest is short for representational state
transfer and I know it probably doesn't
make any sense to you because it was
introduced by PhD student as part of his
thesis but the theory aside rest is
basically a convention for building
these HTTP services so we use simple
HTTP protocol principles to provide
support to create read update and delete
data we refer to these operations all
together as crud operations now let's
explore this convention using a real
world example let's say we have a
company called bitly for renting out
movies we have a client app where we
manage the list of our customers on the
server we should expose a service at an
endpoint like this so vid lucam / api /
customers so the client can send HTTP
requests to this endpoint to talk to our
service now a few things about this
endpoint you need to know first of all
the address can start with HTTP or HTTPS
that depends on the application and its
requirements if you want the data to be
exchanged on a secure Channel you would
use HTTPS after that we have the domain
of the application
next we have slash API this is not
compulsory but you see a lot of
companies follow this convention to
expose their restful services they
include the word API somewhere in the
address it can't be after the domain or
it can be a sub domain like API that
vidlink aam there is no hard and fast
rule after that we have slash customers
which refers to the collection of
customers in our application in the rest
world you refer to this part as a
resource we can expose our resources
such as customers movies rentals on
various endpoints so this is our
endpoint to work with the customers all
the operations around customers such as
creating a customer or updating a
customer would be done by sending an
HTTP request to this endpoint the type
of the HTTP request determines the kind
of the operation so every HTTP request
has what we call a verb or method that
determines its type or intention here
are the standard HTTP methods we have
yet for getting data post or creating
data put for updating data and delayed
for deleting data now let's explore each
of these using our customers example to
get the list of all customers we should
send an HTTP GET request to this address
note the full name customers here it
indicates a list of customers so when we
send an HTTP GET request to this
endpoint our service should send us
something like this so we have an array
of customer objects if you want a single
customer we should include the idea of
that customer in the address then our
server would respond with a customer
object like this now to update a
customer we should send an HTTP put
request to this endpoint and note that
again here we're specifying the idea of
the customer to be updated but also we
should include the customer object in
the body of the request so this is a
complete representation of the customer
object with updated properties
we send this to the server and the
server updates the customer with the
given ID according to these values
similarly to delete a customer we should
send an HTTP delete request to this
endpoint but here we don't need to
include the customer object in the body
of the request because all we need to
delete a customer is an ID and finally
to create a customer we need to send an
HTTP POST request to this endpoint note
that here because we're adding a new
customer you're not dealing with a
specific customer so we don't have the
ID in the address you're working with
the collection of customers so we're
posting a new customer to this collector
and that's why we should include the
customer object in the body of the
request the server gets this object and
creates the customer for us so this is
the restful convention we expose our
resources such as customers using a
simple meaningful address and support
various operations around them such as
creating or updating them using standard
HTTP methods so throughout this section
you're going to learn how to use the
Express framework to build a restful
service from managing the list of
customers however in this section we
won't be doing any database work because
that will bring in additional complexity
our focus will be purely on building
HTTP services and we will use a simple
array in memory to keep the list of our
customers later in the course we'll look
at using a database
so here's the code that we wrote in the
section about node core where I
introduce you to the HTTP module so we
can see with HTTP module we can create a
web server here we have a callback
function that takes two parameters
request and response and with this
request object we can check the URL of
the incoming request so with this we can
define various routes for our
application so if you have a request for
let's say slash API slash courses this
is how we're going to respond to the
client now while this approach certainly
works it's not very maintainable because
as we define more routes for our
application we need to add more if
blocks in this callback function so
that's when a framework comes into the
picture a framework gives our
application a proper structure so we can
easily add more routes while keeping our
application code maintainable now there
are various frameworks out there for
building web applications and web
servers on top of note the most popular
one is Express so if you head over to
NPM JSE org or NPM J is calm here let's
search for Express so the current
version is version 4.2 16.2 let's have a
quick look here so here on the right
side look at the statistics there have
been over 700,000 downloads in the last
day and over 15 million downloads in the
last month it's a very popular framework
it's also very fast lightweight and
perfectly documented so now back in the
terminal let's create a new folder for
this section so I'm gonna call this
Express demo now let's go inside this
folder run NPM init with yes flag so now
we have a package JSON file and finally
we can install Express
beautiful in the next lecture I'm gonna
show you how to build your first web
server using Express
all right now in vs code let's add a new
file index the jas we could also call it
app to J's it doesn't really matter so
in this file first we want to load the
Express module so we use our require
function give it the name of our module
which is Express now this returns a
function we call that Express okay now
we need to call this function like this
and as you can see this returns an
object of type Express by convention we
call this object app so we store the
result in a constant called app so this
represents our application now this app
object has a bunch of useful methods we
have methods like get post put and
delete all these methods correspond to
HTTP verbs or HTTP methods that I told
you about earlier in this section so if
you want to handle an HTTP POST request
to an endpoint you would use app that
post now in this lecture we just want to
use app but yet we want to implement a
couple of endpoints that respond to an
HTTP GET request so this method takes
two arguments the first argument is the
pass or the URL so here I'm going to use
slash to represent the route of the
website
now the second argument is a callback
function this is the function that will
be called when we have an HTTP GET
request to this endpoint okay so this
callback function shall have two
arguments request and response so this
goes to a code block now this request
object has a bunch of useful properties
that gives us information about the
incoming request if you want to learn
about all these properties it's best to
look at the Express documentation
because in this course we're going to
use only a handful of these properties
so head over to Express Jas comm on the
top look at API reference version 4 now
here you can see the request object and
below that you can see all the
properties that are available to you
you have base URL we have body to read
the body of the request cookies fresh
host name IP method original URL
parameters and so on so back to our code
when we get an HTTP GET request to the
root of our website you're gonna respond
with a hello world message so response
dots and hello world so this is how we
define a route we specify the path or
the URL and a callback function which is
also called a route handler now finally
we need to listen on a given point so we
call app that listen we give it a port
number like 3,000 and optionally we can
pass a function that will be called when
the application starts listening on the
given port so once again we use the
arrow function syntax to display
something on the console so console dot
log listening on port 3,000
now back in the terminal note index j s
okay we're listening on port 3000 now
let's switch over to Chrome and go to
localhost port 3000 so here's our hello
word message now let's define another
route so once again we're gonna call app
that get now this one is going to be
slash API slash courses once again we
pass a function with two arguments then
it's request and response and this goes
to a code block now in a real world
scenario here you want to get the list
of courses from the database and return
them but as I told you before in this
section
our focus is purely on building these
endpoints you're not gonna do any
database work so I'm gonna simply return
an array of numbers so response that's
and it passed an array of three numbers
in the future we can replace these
numbers with actual course objects so
save now back in the terminal we have to
stop this process and started the game
so press ctrl + C okay one more time
node index J is now back in Chrome let's
head over to slash API slash courses
look we have an array of three numbers
beautiful so this is what I want you to
pay attention to here in this
implementation we don't have those eve
blocks we define new routes by calling
app that yet and with this structure as
our application grows we can move some
of these routes to different files for
example we can move all the route
related to courses to a separate file
like courses that Jas
so Express gives our application is
skeleton is structure
so far you have noticed that every time
we make a change to this code you have
to go back in the terminal and stop this
process and started the game this is
very tedious so I'm gonna show you a
better way we're gonna install a note
package called note Mon which is short
for node monitor so in the terminal and
p.m. install - G because we want to
install this globally so we can run it
anywhere and the name of the package is
node Mon now as I told you before if
you're on Mac and you haven't configured
the permissions properly in it put sudo
at the front
all right no one is installed so with
this instead of running our application
using node we use node Mon okay now you
can see node Mon is watching all the
files in this folder
any files with any extensions so if we
come back here and make a simple change
and then save the file now look in the
terminal node Hmong restarted our
application or our process due to
changes so we don't have to do this
manually anymore now back in the browser
if you send a request to the root of the
website we can see our new message
displayed here
now one thing we need to improve in this
code is this hard-coded value for the
port so we have used 3000 as an
arbitrary number while this may work on
your development machine it's unlikely
that this is gonna work in a production
environment because when you deploy this
application to a hosting environment the
port is dynamically assigned by the
hosting environment so we can't rely on
3000 to be available so the way to fix
this is by using an environment variable
so typically in hosting environments for
node applications we have this
environment variable called port an
environment variable is basically a
variable that is part of the environment
in which a process runs its value is set
outside this application I'm gonna show
you how that works in a second so in
this application we need to read the
value of this port environment variable
and the way we do that is by using the
process object so we have this global
object called process this object has a
property called M which is short for
environment variables and after that we
add the name of our environment variable
in this case port so if this is set
we're gonna use this otherwise we're
gonna use 3000 now we can store the
result in a constant called port okay
let's delete this and finally we need to
replace 3000 with port and also change
our message accordingly so I'm going to
replace a single coat with backtick so
we can use a template string and here
we're gonna replace 3000 with a dynamic
value so I'm here at dollar sign curly
braces and then add our constant in this
case port okay now back in the terminal
let's run this application using node
maaan
so on this machine you can see I don't
have an environment variable called port
that's why 3000 is used as the port for
this web server now I'm going to set an
environment variable so let's stop this
process on Mac we can set an environment
variable by executing the export command
if you're on Windows you should use set
so export or set now we add the name of
the environment variable in this case
port and set its value I'm going to use
5,000 so now we have this environment
variable called port with the value of
5,000 with this when we run this
application node man
you can see that now we are listening on
port 5000 so this is the proper way to
assign a port to your node applications
you should attempt to read the value of
an environment variable called port if
there is a value you should use that
otherwise use an arbitrary number for
your development machine
you
all right so currently we have a route
for getting the list of courses now in
this lecture I'm going to show you how
to create a route to get a single course
so earlier in the section where I talked
about restful services you learn that in
order to get a single course we should
include the idea of the course and the
URL so our endpoint should be like this
slash API slash courses slash one
assuming that one is the idea of the
course so let's see how we can implement
a route like this so app that get we add
the path that is slash API slash courses
and here we need to define a parameter
so we add : and ID so idea is the name
of our parameter here you could use
anything it doesn't have to be ID it
could be course ID but ID is shorter and
more conventional now we had our route
handler function so request and response
goes to now in order to read this
parameter we use request dot params dot
ID so for now let's just send this to
the client so resource
let's send okay back in the browser now
let's head over to slash API is that
courses slash one so you can see we
successfully read the value of this
parameter also it is possible to have
multiple parameters in a route for
example imagine you're building a
service for powering a block so we could
have a route like this posts here month
so we have two parameters and with this
we can get all the posts for the given
month and the given here now we can read
these parameters just like before
so requested params that year or a month
for this demo let me show you this
requested params object so let's delete
this save back in the browser now let's
head over to API posts 2018
and one so this is our request params
object we have two properties year and
month and their name based on a route
parameters we express we can also get
Kariya string parameters these are
parameters that we add in the URL after
question mark for example we can get all
the posts in January 2018 and sort them
by their name so we add a question mark
sort by set this to name this is a query
string parameter we use query string
parameters to provide additional data to
our back-end services so we use route
parameters for essential or required
values whereas we use query string
parameters for anything that is optional
now let me show you how to read query
parameters so I can view scope instead
of requested params we use request dot
query save back in Chrome and this is
what we get
so query parameters are stored in an
object with a bunch of key value pairs
hi guys thank you for watching my Noah
tutorial I wanted to let you know that
this tutorial is the first hour of my
complete note course where you will
learn how to build a real restful api
using node Express and MongoDB all of
that recorded with the latest version of
node and modern JavaScript so you will
learn new and modern ways of building
applications with node
unlike other courses that only show you
simple the only examples like how to
build a to-do app we're gonna work on a
real-world project a restful api for a
video rental application if you have
taken any of my courses you know i don't
waste your time by explaining the
obvious like what a code editor or
command prompt is we're gonna get
straight to the business and as part of
this i'll be touching on various
important topics that you need to
understand really well including working
with node package manager or npm
asynchronous javascript including
callbacks promises async and await
implementing crud operations data
validations authentication and
authorization using JSON web tokens
including role management handling and
login errors unit and integration
testing test-driven development so you
will see I will build a feature from A
to Z using test-driven development or
TDD and finally we'll deploy this
application to the cloud throughout the
course I will share with you lots of
clean coding and refactoring techniques
security best practices useful libraries
to use as part of your development
common mistakes that many note
developers make and much much more
the course is currently 14 hours long
and I'm planning to add more content to
it in the future you can watch this
course as many times as you want and if
you watch it to the end you will get a
certificate of completion that we can
add to your resume so if you're serious
about adding no to your resume I highly
encourage you to enroll in the course
and don't waste your time jumping from
one tutorial to another so click on the
link in the video description to enrol I
hope to see you in the course
alright now let's implement a new
endpoint to get a single course from the
server so first of all let's change this
back to courses and add the ID parameter
here okay
now on the top let's define an array
called courses so constant courses we
set this to an array and in this array
we're going to have three course objects
so each object should have a couple of
properties ID and name and of course we
can have more but for simplicity I'm
just gonna stick to two properties here
okay now let's duplicate this line and
change the IDs as well as the name two
and three so we have two endpoints want
to get all the courses and the other two
get a single course right in the first
one we're gonna return our courses are
a-okay
right in the second one we should write
some logic to look for the course with
the given ID so let me delete this first
we're gonna call courses that find this
is a method that is available on every
array in JavaScript as an argument to
this method we need to pass a function
this function will be used to find a
course that matches a given criteria so
we use the arrow function syntax C goes
to and here we write some logic that
returns a boolean value this boolean
value determines if this course is the
one we're looking for or not so see that
ID should equal request that params dot
ID
however this requested prams that ID
returns a string so in order for this
comparison to work properly we need to
parse this string into an integer so we
call parse int which is one of the
global functions available in JavaScript
and then get the result and store it and
a constant called course
now you might be asking why I didn't use
var here well that would be perfectly
fine and that's how most JavaScript code
out there is written but going forward
it's best to drop var and either use let
or Const we use let if you want to
define a variable that we can reset
later and we use Const if you want to
define a constant in this case I don't
want to reset the course later in this
function but again that's perfectly fine
to use let here as well it's just
personal preference so we get the course
object now if this course doesn't have a
value in other words if we don't find a
course for the given ID by convention we
should return a response with the HTTP
status code of 404 that means object not
found so this is one of the conventions
of restful api so if the client asks for
a resource but that resource does not
exist on the server we should return a
response with the status code of 404 so
here we call response dot status 404 and
optionally we can send a message to the
client as well so send the course with
the given ID was not found okay now
otherwise if we do have a course with
that ID we're simply going to return
that to the client so response that's
and course now let's test this so back
in the browser let's head over to slash
API slash courses slash one so we have a
course with the ID one and that's why we
get this JSON object in the response
however if I change this to ten we can
this message the course with the given
ID was not found and to ensure that the
status code of this response is 404 we
can open up Chrome developer tools so
right click here go to inspect
and then on the network tab make sure
you don't have a filter here so select
all and then refresh the page by
pressing ctrl R on Windows or command R
on Mac so here's a request that we sent
to the server you can see the status is
404 which means not found
so far we have created two routes that
respond to HTTP GET requests and we use
this route to get all the courses as
well as a single course in this lecture
I'm going to teach you how to respond to
HTTP POST requests so we use an HTTP
POST request to create a new course so
app that post instead of the get method
we use the post method now similar to
the get method we need to specify a path
so that should be a slash API slash
courses because we're going to post to
the collection of courses that's why we
use the plural name here then we add our
route handler so request and response
goes to code block now I'm going to add
some line break here so I can easily see
this video all right so in this route
handler we need to read the course
object that should be in the body of the
request use these properties to create a
new course object and then add that
course object to our courses array so
let's create a new course object
constant course again I'm using a
constant here because we're not going to
reset this course object later so let's
set this to a new object now here
because we are not working with a
database we need to manually assign an
ID so ID so we get the number of
elements in our courses array so courses
dot length and simply add one to it in
the future when we work with the
database the ID will be assigned by the
database next is the name property now
we need to read this from the body of
the request
so request that body that name so here
I'm assuming that in the request body we
have an object and that object has a
name property now in order for this line
to work we need to enable parsing of
JSON objects in the body of the request
because by default this feature is not
enabled in express so on the top after
we get the app object
we need to call app that use and here we
call Express dot JSON now this may look
a little bit strange or unfamiliar to
you but don't worry later in this
section we're going to explore this in
detail basically what we're doing here
is adding a piece of middleware
so when we call Express the JSON meta
this method returns a piece of
middleware and then we call app dot use
to use that middleware in the request
processing pipeline again we're going to
explore that in detail later in the
section so back to our new route handler
you have a course object next we push it
in our array so courses dot push course
and finally by convention when we post
an object to the server when the server
creates a new object or a new resource
you should return that object in the
body of the response so response that's
and course
the reason for this is because we are
assigning this ID on the server so we
need to return this course object to the
client because chances are the client
needs to know the idea of this new
object or this new resource so this is
how we handle HTTP POST requests in the
next lecture I'm going to show you how
to test this endpoint
all right to call HTTP services we use a
Chrome extension called postman so if
you have an installed postman before
search for Chrome postman here is
postman simply add it to Chrome ok done
now you can open this from the apps menu
here postman I hear it's asking you to
sign up for an account but you don't
have to do this there's a link here take
me straight to the app alright now on
this page we can create a new HTTP
request
so from this drop-down list we set the
type to a post request you put the URL
here in this case that's HTTP localhost
on my machine I'm using port 3000 to
host this application API slash courses
now we need to set the body of this
request from this list select raw and
then
JSON so with this we can put a JSON
object in the body of the request so
let's add an object here and give it a
name property so name we set this to new
course and then finally send okay if you
scroll down you can see the status of
the request is 200 which means the
request was handled successfully and
here's the body of the response so IDs
for because now we have four courses in
our array and this is the same name that
we send to the server so this is how we
test HTTP services is in postman now in
this implementation we have assumed that
there is an object with the name
property in the body of the request what
if the client forgets to send this
property or sends an invalid name
perhaps a name that is too short that's
where input validation comes into the
picture and that's the topic for the
next lecture
in this lecture I'm going to show you
how to do input validation so as a
security best practice you should never
ever ever trust what the client sends
you
you should always validate the input so
in this particular example because we're
dealing with a simple object with only
one property that is named we can write
some validation logic like this
so if requests the body that name
doesn't exist or requests that body the
name that length is less than 3 then
we're gonna return an error to the
client the restful convention is to
return a response with the HTTP status
code or 400 that means bad requests so
to do this recall response that status
400 and then we can send an error
message in this case we can write a
generic error message like name is
required and should be minimum three
characters in your implementation you
may want to differentiate the errors for
example if the client didn't send the
name property perhaps you would just
respond with name is required or if they
did send the name but the name was not
long enough you could send a different
error message and then finally we
returned here because we don't want the
rest of this function to be executed so
this is the basic idea however in a real
world application it's more likely that
you'll be working with a complex object
something more complex than this course
object here you don't want to write a
complex validation logic like this at
the beginning of your route handler so
let me introduce you to a new package
that makes it really easy for you to
validate the input so on Google if you
search for NPM joy with I look here is
the first link so here you can see joy
has been downloaded over to
150,000 times or the past day and over
three million times over the past month
it's a very popular package also here on
this page you can see some sample code
and link to your official documentation
now let me show you how to replace this
validation logic with joy
so first back in terminal let's install
joy so you can see it at the time of
recording this video the latest version
is version 13 point 1.0 if you want to
make sure that you have the exact same
experience as what I'm going to show you
in this video then install this exact
version so npm install joy at thirteen
point one point zero okay now back in
the code on the top we need to load this
module so require joy get the result and
store it in a constant called joy with a
capital J because what is returned from
this module is a class and as I told you
before in JavaScript we use Pascal
naming convention to name our classes so
the first letter of every word should be
uppercase also as a best practice with
all your required calls on top of the
file this way you can easily see what
are the dependencies of this module so
this module index module is dependent
upon two modules one is joy the other is
Express okay so we have this joy class
now packing our route handler now with
joy first we need to define a schema
schema defines the shape of our objects
what properties do we have in that
object what is the type of each property
do we have an email do we have a string
what are the minimum or maximum number
of characters do we have a number what
range should that number be so this is
the job of a schema so here first I'm
going to define a schema constant schema
we set it to an object this is the shape
of our course object so here we want to
have a name property and we said this to
joy
dot string so we're telling joyed that
this is a string and it should have
minimum three characters and it should
be required so it has a very fluent API
again you can look at the documentation
to see all the methods that are
available to you so here's our a schema
now we call joy that validate and we
give it request that body as well as our
schema now this validate method returns
an object let's store that in a constant
called result for this demo I'm gonna
log this result on the console so before
we go any further let's save this go
back to the postman let's create another
course now back in the terminal so this
is a result object it has two properties
error and value only one of these can
have a value so in this case because we
sent a valid course object we have that
object here as the value of the value
property and you can see error is not if
we send an invalid object value will be
null and error will be set let me show
you so I can postman let's remove the
name property send now back in the
terminal okay look so here's the result
object this is the error property it's
set to an object that has validation
error child name fails because name is
required so back to a route handler
instead of this manual validation logic
we can check the value of result that
error property so if result that error
then we're gonna send a response with
status code of 400 and in the body of
the response for now we can simply add
result an error okay and we don't need
this constant along anymore
save now back in postman one more time
I'm gonna send this empty object now
look at the response so this is what we
get an object with these properties is
joy name details which is an array of
error messages so here's the first
message name is required now this object
is too complex to send to the client
perhaps you want to simplify this so
back in the code one simple solution is
to go to the details array get the first
element and then access the message
property or instead of using the first
element you may want to access all
elements in this array get their message
property and concatenate them that's
entirely up to you so save one more time
let's send an invalid request and now we
get name is required if we go to our
request and add the name property but
set it to a string that is only 1
character now we get a different error
name length must be at least 3
characters long so you can see joy makes
it really easy to validate the input and
return proper error messages to the
client
all right now let's see how we can
update a course so let's add a new route
handler app we use the put method for
updating resources now the path should
be slash API slash courses and here we
need a route parameter because we're
dealing with your specific course
so ID now our route handler function
request son response goes to a code
block alright now here's the logic we
need to implement first we need to look
up this course with this given ID so
look up the course if the course doesn't
exist if not existing we need to return
404 that means resource not found
otherwise we need to validate the course
make sure it's in good shape
if invalid we need to return a 400 error
which means that request and if you get
here that means everything is good so
you update the course and return the
updated course to the client this is the
logic we need to implement so we already
have some code that we can reuse here so
I'm not going to type everything by hand
I'm gonna copy some code from our other
route handlers so first we want to look
up the course and if it doesn't exist
you want to return a 404 error for that
I'm gonna go to this other rat handler
where we get a single course this is the
logic we're interested in so we look up
the course and if it doesn't exist we
return a 404 error so copy these two
lines we're done with the first part the
second part is all about validation for
that I'm gonna go to our post endpoint
so here we need to copy the schema as
well as this line for validating the
request body using joy and there is a
problem with this approach the problem
is in this case we have a very simple
schema what if you are dealing with a
complex object with quite a few
properties then
or validation logic would be duplicated
in two different round handlers so let's
just copy the code for now and then
we'll come back and refactor it to make
it better so copy these few lines and
paste it here
so we're validating and if it's invalid
we need to return a 400 error so I
forgot to copy that line here if you
have an error in the result we're gonna
return it's 400 error okay
so let's copy that as well so this is
our second part we have this schema we
validate and if you have an error we
return a 400 error we're done with the
second part now the third part so at
this point we have a course object we
can update its properties so of course
that name we said that to request the
body the name and of course if we have
other properties we'll set them here as
well so we're done with opting in the
course and finally we need to return the
updated course to the client so response
that's and course this is how we handle
an HTTP put request now I told you that
we have duplicated this validation logic
so I'm going to extract these few lines
into a separate function that we can
reuse both in this route handler for
handling our HTTP put requests as well
as the other one we wrote in the last
lecture for creating a course
so let's define a function here and call
it validate course we give it a course
object now in this function we should
have the schema as well as this line for
validating the course so cut these few
lines place it here now instead of
validating requested body you're gonna
validate the argument that is passed to
this method so that would be the course
object now finally we can simply return
this result to the caller there is no
need to define a constant so with this
new implementation we have all the
validation logic in one place now we can
reuse this so here is our put method
we define a constant call result and
study to validate course and as an
argument we pass request dot body now we
can make this code a little bit cleaner
and shorter by using object
destructuring feature and modern
JavaScript so look here we get this
result object and we're accessing result
that error property in two different
places since all we are interested in is
this error property we can get this
using object destructuring so let me
duplicate this line and show you how
object restructuring works with object
is structuring when declaring a variable
or a constant we add curly braces and
then here we add the property of the
target object so in this case the target
object that is returned from our
validate course method has two
properties error and value in this case
we just want the error property so we
put that between curly braces so this is
equivalent to getting result that error
one instead of using this notation we
use this notation okay
and with this we don't have to repeat
result that error in two different
places we can simply use error okay so
this is object destructuring now we
don't need this first line anymore and
finally before we finish this lecture we
need to make one more change in this
code so we need to use this new way of
validating a course in the route handler
for handling our HTTP POST requests so
copy this is our handler for creating a
new course now we don't need to use this
schema here we moved all that logic to
our validate course function so all
these few lines here for validating the
request body and sending the 400 error
I'm going to delete this and paste the
code that we copied from the other
method so we call validate course use
object D structure and syntax and if you
have an error you return the 400
response to the client now finally let's
test our new endpoint for updating a
course
so back in postman we need to change the
type of this HTTP request to put change
the URL and add a valid course ID like
one here we have a pilot course object
with name set to new course so send and
we get a 200 response which is
successful and here is the updated
course so if you open any new tab and
send an HTTP GET request to localhost /
api / courses now you should see the
list of our courses so our first course
it's name is up data perfect now let's
test the other scenarios what if you
send an invalid ID so 10 send the course
with the given ID was not found and you
can see the response is 404 which means
not found and finally what if you send a
valid course ID but an invalid course
object so I'm gonna remove the name
property send now you can see we have a
bad request for 400
error and here's error message name is
required next I'm gonna show you how to
handle HTTP delete requests
so out of all the crud operations you
have implemented create read and update
so in this lecture I'm gonna show you
how to respond to HTTP delete requests
it's very simple and similar to what we
have done so far so here's our app
object we call the delete method give it
a pass that is slash API slash courses
and of course we need a parameter
because we're working with a specific
course then a raft Handler request our
response goes to the code block now here
first we need to look up the course the
course would be given ID if it doesn't
exist then we need to return 404
otherwise we're going to delete it and
by convention return the same course the
course that was deleted so again I'm
gonna borrow some code from our other
grant handlers to look up the course and
return a 404 error I'm gonna go back for
ramp handler for the HTTP put request so
these first two lines is for looking up
the course and returning a 404 error so
copy these two lines back here that is
our first part done now to delete a
course first we need to find the index
of this course in our courses array so
courses dot index of course
we get the index store it in a constant
and then we can use this splice method
to remove an object from our courses
array so courses dot splice we go to
this index and remove one object so this
is the delete part and finally we need
to return the response to the client so
response let's send this course object
now let's test this
so back in postman let's change put to
delete first I want to send an invalid
course ID like ten send so we get a 404
error not found with this message
perfect now let's delete the first
course course with the ID one send so we
get the same course object in the
response and if we go to our second tab
where we have the list of our courses so
look we have an HTTP GET request to the
send point let's send this one more time
okay now look we don't have our first
course anymore we only have courses with
ID two and three all right before we go
any further I realize we have a bug or
actually three bugs in this code so look
at the handler or responding to put
requests to this endpoint if we don't
have a course with the given ID we
return the 404 error to the client but
at this point we should exit this route
handler otherwise the rest of this code
will be executed so the proper way to
implement this round handler is like
this so if you don't have this course we
return the response and then exit the
function or a shorter way to write the
same code is to put the return here and
then we don't need the code block so we
can put everything in one line okay now
to make this code cleaner let's use the
same technique in case we have an
invalid request so we simply return
and then we don't need the code lock
anymore that's much more elegant you
have the same issue in the handler for
delete requests so if you don't have a
course here we should return immediately
the same is true when getting a single
course so if we don't have a course with
the given ID we return the 404 error and
also return from this function
immediately now finally let's have a
look at the handler for HTTP POST
requests here it is again I'm gonna use
the same technique to clean up this code
so if you have an error we simply return
and get rid of the extra noise in the
code that's much better
all right now it's time for an exercise
so from this lecturer we're gonna start
building the back-end services for our
VIP little acacia as I told you before
Whitley is an imaginary service for
renting out movies so throughout this
course we're going to build the backend
of Whitley bit by bit
your first task is to create a service
from managing the list of genres so each
movie as a genre like action horror
whatever we should have an endpoint for
getting the list of all genres because
somewhere in our client applications
perhaps we have a drop-down list for the
user to select a genre so we need an
endpoint to get all the genres we should
also be able to create a new genre as
well as update or delete an existing one
so before going any further I want you
to put what you have learned so far in
practice so even if you're an
experienced developer don't say no mosh
I know how to do this this is so easy I
know it's easy but what matters now is
that I want you to get used to this
theme tax so go ahead start a new
project from scratch call it bitly and
build this HTTP service for managing the
list of genres you can see my solution
attached to this lecture